Register of the Paul Robert Hanna Papers, 1920-1997
Hoover Institution Archives
- PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES, 1900-1983 (Boxes 18-34)
  - Chronological file
    - 1968
      - August 9-12, seminar, "The Role of Higher Education in National Development in Asia," Seoul, Korea
        - Proceedings, papers, reports (Box 32, Folder 1)
        - Seoul (Folder 2)
        - TAF Quarterly (Folder 3)
      - November 11, conference, Como Conference on Learning, Como, Italy (Folder 4)
      - November 12-13--see SUBJECT FILE, Peace Corps-University of Hawaii Study Committee, meetings
      - November-December, trip to Japan (Folder 5)
      - December 13-22--see SUBJECT FILE, Peace Corps-University of Hawaii Study Committee, meetings
    - 1969
      - General (Folder 6)
      - February, August, December--see SUBJECT FILE, Houghton Mifflin Company, Spelling textbook project, promotional materials, miscellaneous campaigns
      - April 3-4, consultation, University of Massachusetts (Folder 7)
    - 1970
      - General (Folder 8)
      - March 3-14, conference, Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development, Asilomar, California (Folder 9)
      - August 24-26, workshop, Education Service Center, Johnson County teachers, Fort Worth, Texas (Folder 10)
    - 1971 (Folder 11)
    - 1972 (Folder 12-13)
    - 1973 (Folder 14)
    - 1974 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - 1975 (Folder 2)
    - 1976 (Folder 3)
    - 1977
      - General (Folder 4)
      - November 16, speaking engagement, Sons in Retirement, Palo Alto, California (Folder 5)
    - 1978 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1979 (Folder 8)
    - 1983 (Folder 9)
  - Boards and consulting
    - Asia Foundation (Folder 10)
    - East-West Center (Folder 11)
    - Field Enterprises, 1969-1970 (Folder 12)
    - Infomedica, 1973-74 (Folder 13)
    - Infomedica, 1973-74 (Box 34, Folder 1-2)
    - Nueva School, 1971-73 (Folder 3)
    - Pacific Studies, 1971 (Folder 4)
    - Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group, 1970 (Folder 5)
    - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Office of Education, 1966-1974 (Folder 6)
    - U.S. Department of State, 1971-72
      - General (Folder 7)
      - Agency for International Development (Folder 8)
    - United World Colleges, 1970-72 (Folder 9)
    - World Board of Trade, 1972-74 (Folder 10)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1932-1977 (Boxes 34-41)
  Manuscripts, drafts, typescripts, notes, printed articles filed alphabetically by title or subject.
  - Unfinished manuscripts with related correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Education for developing nations (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Education for the future (Folder 2)
    - Global studies (Folder 3)
    - "Prospects in Education" (for UNESCO) (Folder 4)
    - Research on values (Folder 5)
    - Role of accidents in career choices (Folder 6)
  - Untitled drafts and notes (Folder 7)
  - "Arithmetic Used in an Activity Program"--see "Spelling--From Spoken Word to Written Symbol"
  - Aviation Education Source Book (director of project), New York, Hastings House, Publishers, Inc., 1946. Printed copy. (Folder 8)
  - "The Care and Feeding of Spaceship Earth," 1975. Typescript (photocopy). (Folder 9)
  - Commencement address, Castilleja School, n.d.--see SUBJECT FILE, Castilleja School
  - Commencement address, Hamline University, 1979----see SUBJECT FILE, Hamline University
  - "The Community School and Larger Geographic Areas," chapter XIV of The Fifty-Second Yearbook of the National Society for the Study of Education, part II, Nelson B. Henry, editor, Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1953. Printed copy. (See also SUBJECT FILE, World Book Encyclopedia) (Folder 10)
  - "Content in the Social Studies: Generalizations from the Social Sciences," from The Thirty-Second Yearbook of the National Council for the Social Studies, Washington, D.C., National Education Association, 1962. Printed copy with related correspondence. (Folder 11)
  - "Conventional and Unconventional Education for Newly Developed Countries," from American's Emerging Role in Overseas Education, Syracuse, New York, Syracuse University School of Education, 1962. Printed copy. (Folder 12)
  - "Curriculum and Instruction: A Proposal Concerning the NEA's Future Role in These Areas," National Education Association Journal, January, 1963. Printed copy with related correspondence. (Folder 13)
  - "Debate: Resolved, That a National Curriculum Commission is Desirable," n.d. Newspaper clipping. (Folder 14)
  - "Design for a National Curriculum," The Nation's Schools, September, 1958. Printed copy. (Folder 15)
  - "Designing a Multi-Disciplinary and Coordinated Social Studies program," speech----see PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES, 1965, April 24-28
  - "Educating for Emerging Multinational Communities," 1965. Two drafts and galley proofs, typescript and holograph (Folder 16)
  - "Educating Men for Economic Productivity," unpublished paper, Stanford, California, Hoover Institution and Library, in cooperation with the Foreign Operations Administration, Program on Overseas Development, 1955. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 17)
  - "Education: An Instrument of U.S. Foreign Policy," 1954-55. Correspondence, notes, and printed matter in preparation for an article. (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - "Education and Air Affairs," Air Affairs: An International Quarterly, Autumn, 1947. Printed copy. (Folder 2)
  - "Education for an Air World," Air Affairs: An International Journal, December, 1946. Printed copy. (Folder 3)
  - "Education for All American Children (Focus on Values and Techniques)," unpublished paper, Washington, D.C., Education Policies Commission, National Education Association of the United States and the American Association of School Administrators, April 1947. Typescript (mimeographed copy) with related correspondence. (Folder 4-5)
  - "Education for Survival," unpublished paper, n.d. Typescript. (Folder 6)
  - "Education for Survival and Progress," three drafts, n.d. Typescripts with related correspondence. (Folder 7-8)
  - "Education in the Far East," with Sidney C. High, Jr., Phi Delta Kappan, June, 1956. Printed copy with related correspondence. (Folder 9)
  - "An Educator's Preface," to Classroom Out-of-Doors, Wilbur Schramm, author, Kalamazoo, Michigan, Sequoia Press, 1969. Printed copy. (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - "Generalizations From Social Sciences Useful in Social Studies Programs," n.d. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 2)
  - "Generalizations and Universal Values: Their Implications for the Social-Studies Program," Chapter II of Social Studies in the Elementary School, The Fifty-Sixth Yearbook of the National Society for the Study of Education, Nelson B. Henry, editor, Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1957. Printed copy with related correspondence. (Folder 3)
  - "A Guide to Geographic Content in the Social Studies," with Malcolm P. Douglass, Education, September, 1956. Printed copy. (Folder 4)
  - "I Recall," January 12, 1976. Typescript. (Folder 5)
  - "The Instructional Dilemma Today - One Educator's Perspective," January 20, 1977. Typescript (photocopy). (Folder 6)
  - "International Education," two drafts, 1963, Typescript (carbon copy) with related correspondence. (Folder 7)
  - "Mounting a National Effort in the Social Studies," The National Elementary Principal, May 1963. Printed copy. (Folder 8)
  - National Curriculum Commission, proposal for
    - General (Folder 9)
    - American Association of School Administrators (Folder 10)
    - Briggs, Thomas H., "Proposal For a Curriculum Commission," January 1959 (Folder 11)
    - Center for the Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Stanford, conference, January 26-30, 1959 (Folder 12)
    - Conference of Policies and Strategy for Strengthening the Curriculum of American Public Schools, Stanford University, January 24-27, 1959 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Folder 2)
    - Education Digest, 1958 (Folder 3)
    - Harvard Educational Review, 1959-1960 (Folder 4)
    - "A National Commission for Curriculum Research and Development," article for the Harvard Educational Review, September 1959. Typescript (photocopy). (Folder 5)
    - "A National Curriculum Center: Threat or Promise?" paper presented at Harvard University, July 19, 1959. Typescript. (Folder 6)
    - National Education Association condensation of Harvard article (Folder 7)
    - The Nation's School article, September 1958
      - Correspondence, 1958-59 (Folder 8)
      - Critical comments, 1958-59 (Folder 9)
      - "Design For a National Curriculum," by P.R. Hanna (Folder 10)
      - Distribution list (Folder 11)
      - Doctoral students' comments, 1958 (Folder 12)
      - Opinion poll (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Reprints and editorial follow-up (Folder 2)
    - The Nation's Schools
      - "Looking Forward - We Need a Common Approach," reprint, November 1958 (Folder 3)
      - "Looking Forward - Three Big Decisions," reprint, May 1959 (Folder 4)
    - Phi Delta Kappan, 1961-63 (Folder 5)
    - Publicity, 1958-59 (Folder 6)
    - Questions raised by groups at Glencott (Folder 7)
    - Reed, Elton, "Which Is Better?" January 28, 1960. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 8)
    - St. Louis speech, June 29, 1959 (Folder 9)
    - Tyler proposal, 1957-58 (Folder 10)
  - "The NEA's Future Role in Curriculum and Instruction," unpublished paper, Denver, National Education Association Convention, 1962. Typescript. (Folder 11)
  - Notes removed from desk when moved to SIDEC (Folder 12)
  - "Organization and Administration of the Public Schools, Territory of Hawaii, General Curriculum and Vocational Curriculum," with Henry B. McDaniel, Stanford, California, 1957. Printed copy. (Folder 13)
  - "Pacific Northwest, Regional Teachers College," with others, Stanford, California, Stanford University, 1940. Typescript (mimeographed copy) (Folder 14)
  - "Paul Hanna Interviews Arnold Toynbee," Phi Delta Kappan, December, 1967. Typescripts with related correspondence. (Folder 15)
  - "Philippine Educators Show the Way," Education, June, 1956. Printed copy with related correspondence. (Folder 16)
  - "Preparing for Careers in Education," Stanford University School of Education Bulletin, December, 1948. Printed copy. (Folder 17)
  - "Programs of Study for Geography," article, NEA Journal, January 1965. Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - "Proposed--A National Commission for Curriculum Research and Development," draft and final version, Phi Delta Kappan, May, 1961. Typescript and printed copy. (Folder 2)
  - "Readings in Methods of Social Change," 1932. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 3)
  - "Remarks by Paul R. Hanna," speech in response to Distinguished Service Award, Silver Jubilee, Philippine Public School Teachers Association, April 9, 1958. Typescript (mimeographed copy). (Folder 4)
  - "Report on Germany," 1947. Typescript (with annotations) and related correspondence. (Folder 4A)
  - Report to Council of National Defense Coordinator of Commercial and Cultural Relations Between the American Republics," unpublished document, 1941. Typescript. (Folder 5)
  - Response to reviews of Phoneme-Grapheme Correspondences as Cues to Spelling Improvement--see SUBJECT FILE, Houghton Mifflin Company, spelling project, correspondence, 1967, April
  - "Review of contract between the Philippine Department of Education and Stanford University," 1956--see SUBJECT FILE, United States Agency for International Development, University of Philippines-Stanford University contract
  - "Revising the Social Studies: What is Needed?" two drafts and final version, Social Education, April, 1963. Typescript with related correspondence. (Folder 6)
  - "The Right to Rest, Recreation and Adventure," Frontiers of Democracy," Vol. 8, No. 70, May 15, 1942. Printed copy. (Folder 7)
  - "Social Studies for Today," The Journal, National Education Association, January, 1956. Printed copy with related correspondence (Folder 8)
  - "Society-Child-Curriculum," in Education 2000 A.D., Clarence W. Hunnicutt, editor, Syracuse, New York, Syracuse University Press, 1956. Printed copy with related correspondence. (Folder 9)
  - "Some Quotes From H.G. Wells on 'The Idea of a World Encyclopedia' From Harper's Magazine for April 1937," 1959--see SUBJECT FILE, World Book Encyclopedia
  - "Spelling and Communications Theory: A Model and Annotated Bibliography," 1963--see SUBJECT FILE, Houghton Mifflin Company, spelling project, reprints
  - "Spelling as a School Subject: A Brief History," with Jean S. Hanna, The National Elementary Principal, May 1959. Printed copy with related correspondence. (Folder 10)
  - "Spelling--From Spoken Word to Written Symbol," Elementary School Journal, February, 1953. Reprinted in The Education Digest, May 1953. Printed copy. (Folder 11)
  - "Spelling--From Spoken Word to Written Symbol," with James T. Moore, and "Arithmetic Used in an Activity Program," with others, in Research in the Three R's, C.W. Hunnicutt and William J. Iverson, editors, New York, Harper and Row, 1958. Printed copy. (Folder 12)
  - "Spelling Today," reprint, The Instructor, November 1960. Printed copy. (Folder 13)
  - "Spelling Today," with Jean Hanna, 1960--see SUBJECT FILE, Houghton Mifflin Company, spelling project, correspondence, 1969
  - "The Teaching of Spelling," July 1965. Typescript. (Folder 14)
  - "The Teaching of Spelling," with Jean Hanna, 1964-1965--see SUBJECT FILE, Houghton Mifflin Company, spelling project, reprints
  - "We Practice Conservation," as told to Alvin C. Klotz, CTA Journal, November 1957. Printed copy with related correspondence. (Folder 15)
  - "A World Grid of Regional Training Centers," draft, carbon, and final version, Office on Institutional Projects Abroad, National Education Association, Bulletin, June 1956. Typescripts with related correspondence. (Folder 16)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1930-1982 (Boxes 41-129)
  Correspondence, reports, studies, printed matter, clippings, charts, and other materials filed alphabetically by subject or title.
  - Agricultural Development Council (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Alexandria High School Alumni Association, 1970 (Folder 2)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 1970-75 (Folder 3)
  - American Association of Emeriti, 1967 (Folder 4)
  - American Association of Retired Persons, 1968, 1978 (Folder 5)
  - American Council on Education (see also Education and World Affairs)
    - Commission on International Education
      - Correspondence
        - 1967-1968 (Folder 6)
        - 1968-1969 (Folder 7)
      - Meetings
        - 1961-1963
          - General (Folder 8)
          - Written work (Folder 9)
          - July 25, 1963 (Folder 10)
          - September 27, 1963 (Folder 11)
        - 1964
          - March 3, 1964 (Folder 12)
          - November 15-16, 1964 (Folder 13)
        - 1965
          - Proposed Stanford seminar, Fall 1965 (Folder 14)
          - November 12, 1965 (Box 42, Folder 1)
        - October 31, 1966 (Folder 2)
        - 1967
          - March 24, 1967 (Folder 3)
          - April 17, 1967 (Folder 4)
          - October 18, 1967 (Folder 5)
      - Paper, "International Migration of Intellectual Talent," 1966 (Folder 6)
      - Policy statement, 1963 (Folder 7)
      - Projects and concerns of commission staff, 1965 (Folder 8)
      - Task force on Agency for International Development-University Relations
        - "AID and the Universities," 1964 (Folder 9)
        - Report drafts, 1963 (Folder 10-11)
    - Correspondence, 1971-72 (Folder 12)
    - Meeting, October 8-9, 1959 (Folder 13)
    - Proposal for an international think tank, 1967 (Folder 14)
  - American Educational Publications (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - American Educational Research Association
    - Bylaws and correspondence, March-August 1966 (Folder 2)
    - Encyclopedia of Educational Research, 1967 (Folder 3)
    - Meetings, February 1966
      - Agenda (Folder 4)
      - Committee on International Relations (Folder 5)
      - Committee on International Relations and Comparative Education Society (Folder 6)
    - Plans (Folder 7)
    - Sig On the Creation and Utilization of Curriculum Knowledge, 1978-1980 (Folder 8)
  - American Institute for Economic Research, 1973, 1980 (Folder 9)
  - Ando, Terutsugu, "Paul Hanna," 1984 (Folder 9A)
  - Arnett, Dixon (Folder 10)
  - Asia Foundation, 1968-1976 (Folder 11)
  - Atlantic Council, 1967-1973 (Folder 12)
  - Atlantic Institute--see Committee on Atlantic Studies
  - Bartkey, John, "Value," March 15, 1961 (Folder 13)
  - Bloomsbury West, Inc., 1980 (Folder 14)
  - Bohemian Club
    - General, 1967-69 (Folder 15)
    - Camp Sempervirens
      - General, 1972-77 (Folder 16)
      - Fund, 1973-75 (Folder 17)
      - History, 1973 (Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Folder 19)
    - Events (Folder 20)
    - Photographic Committee (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Bohemian Grove, 1969-1974 (Folder 2)
  - Building America textbook series
    - General (Folder 3-5)
    - Building America, "Russia," copy marked by Soviet Consulate in New York, 1944 (Folder 6)
    - Comments on Building America, 1935-1942 (Folder 7)
    - Controversy concerning adoption of Building America textbooks by California public schools
      - 1944-49 (Folder 8-9)
      - 1944-49 (Box 45, Folder 1)
      - Miscellany (Folder 2)
      - California Legislature, Joint Fact- Finding Committee to the Fifty-Sixth California Legislature, "Un-American Activities in California," second report, 1945, and seventh report, 1953 (Folder 3)
      - California State Board of Education
        - Members (Folder 4)
        - Minutes, July 12-13, 1946 (Folder 5)
        - Proceedings, August 24, 1946 (Folder 6)
        - Proceedings, October 4, 1946 (Folder 7)
        - "Proceedings for Adoption of Building America as Supplementary Texts by the State Board of Education, Answer to Protest of Aaron M. Sargent," 1946 (Folder 8)
        - "Summary of Actions of the State Board of Education and the State Curriculum Commission in Adopting Building America, " by Roy Simpson and H. McPherson, California Schools, April 1947 (Folder 9)
      - California State Curriculum Commission
        - Proceedings, August 24, 1946 (Folder 10)
        - Report on the adoption of history and geography textbooks, July 1, 1946 (Folder 11)
        - "Response to the 'Complaint for Redress of Grievances' filed in behalf of the California Society of the Sons of the American Revolution by Mr. Aaron M. Sargent, Attorney-at-Law," addressed to the members of the Education Committee of the California State Senate, by Roy E. Simpson, Chairman of the State Curriculum Commission (Folder 12)
      - California State Department of Education, biographical sketches, Superintendent of Public Instruction, Members, State Board of Education, Members, State Curriculum Commission, April 1, 1947 (Folder 13)
      - California State Senate
        - Bills 97 and 1029, May 28 and June 20, 1947 (Folder 14)
        - Daily Journal, April 7, 1947 (Folder 15)
        - Investigating Committee on Education
          - Complaint and brief, filed by Aaron M. Sargent and the California Society of the Sons of the American Revolution, February 21, 1947 (Folder 16)
          - Critical Analysis of "Building America Series," by R.E. Combs, n.d. (Folder 17)
        - Reports, 1947 and 1948 (Box 46, Folder 1)
        - Statement of the editors of Building America, February, 1947 (Folder 2)
      - Pressure groups active on California educational practices
        - General (Folder 3)
        - All-American Committee (Folder 4)
        - Friends of the Public Schools (Folder 5)
        - Sargent, Aaron M. (Folder 6)
      - United States Congress, "A Bill of Grievances," constitutional petition for the redress of grievances, presented to the Senate Judiciary Committee and the House Un-American Activities Committee, National Society, Sons of the American Revolution, 1949 (Folder 7)
      - United States House of Representatives, Special Committee to Investigate Tax Exempt Foundations, excerpt from stenographic transcript of hearings, May 26, 1954 (Folder 8)
    - Correspondence
      - Confidential, 1938-1946 (Folder 9)
      - 1935-39 (Folder 10)
      - August 1945 -December 1946 (Folder 11)
      - January-June 1947 (Folder 12)
      - July-December 1947 (Folder 13)
      - January 1948 -August 1949 (Box 47, Folder 1)
      - 1961, 1968 (Folder 2)
    - Editorial changes, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - Manual on the use of Building America, outline and draft (Folder 4)
    - Newman, Robert Ernest, Jr., History of a Civic Education Project Implementing the Social-Problems Technique of Instruction, dissertation submitted to the School of Education of Stanford University, 1960 (Folder 5)
    - Topics suggested by department members for 1945-46 publishing schedule (Folder 6)
  - California
    - Department of Education, correspondence, 1973 (Folder 7)
    - State Legislature (Folder 8)
  - California Coastline Zone Conservation Commission, 1972-76 (Folder 9)
  - California Council on Teacher Education (Folder 10)
  - California Farm Bureau Federation, 1976 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - California Land Conservation Act, 1965 (Folder 2)
  - California Public Outdoor Recreation Plan, 1960
    - Part I (Folder 3)
    - Part II (Folder 4)
  - California State Committee on Public Education, Project V, Curriculum, 1966-68
    - General, 1966-67 (Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1966-68 (Folder 6)
    - Drafting final report, 1966-67 (Folder 7-9)
    - Staff summary reports, 1966 (Folder 10-11)
  - California State Department of Education, Advisory Committee on the National Defense Education Act, 1963
    - January 24-25
    - April 25-27 (Box 49, Folder 1-2)
    - June 28-29 (Folder 3)
  - California state printing of textbooks, 1974-75 (Folder 4-5)
  - California State Reconstruction and Reemployment Commission, "Manpower for California Schools," January, and "Reports of Committees and Proposal for a California Council on Teacher Education," May, 1945
  - "Carnegie Quarterly," 1978-79 (Folder 7)
  - Castilleja School
    - General
      - 1970-76 (Folder 8)
      - 1971-73 (Folder 9)
    - Fundraising, 1977-1980 (Box 50, Folder 1-2)
  - Chicago Public Schools
    - Consulting, March 11-13, 1959 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1957-59 (Folder 4)
    - Materials, 1957-59 (Folder 5)
  - Cleveland Conference, 1953-1980
    - Meetings
      - December 1953 -December 1955 (Folder 6)
      - December 7-8, 1956 (Folder 7)
      - December 6-7, 1957 (Folder 8)
      - December 1958 -December 1959 (Folder 9)
      - December 1960 (Folder 10)
      - December 1961 (Folder 11)
      - November 30-December 1, 1962 (Folder 12)
      - November 29-30, 1963 (Folder 13)
      - December 4-5, 1964 (Folder 14)
      - December 3-4, 1965 (Folder 15)
      - December 2-3, 1966 (Folder 16)
    - Membership lists and correspondence
      - 1962-66 (Folder 17)
      - 1970-1980 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Commission on Coping with Interdependence, 1975-76 (Folder 2-3)
  - Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs (Folder 4)
  - Committee on Atlantic Studies
    - Correspondence
      - 1968-1970 (Folder 5)
      - 1971-73 (Folder 6)
    - Meetings
      - March 12, 1966, minutes (Folder 7)
      - 1968
        - February 19, subcommittee chaired by Frank Munk (Folder 8)
        - September 9-14, full committee (Folder 9)
        - September 12, European and North American sections (Folder 10)
        - April 20, North American section (Folder 11)
      - 1969
        - February 15, North American section (Box 52, Folder 1)
        - July, Board of Directors (Folder 2)
      - 1970, February 28, North American section (Folder 3)
      - 1971 (Folder 4)
    - Membership, 1969 (Folder 5)
    - Proposal, January 24, 1968 (Folder 6)
  - Comparative Education Society
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Board of Directors, 1967-68 (Folder 8)
  - "Dow Theory Forecasts," September-October 1980 (Folder 9)